Guide to the Willie Varela Papers, ca. 1960-1995
Department of Special Collections
Willie Varela Papers,
ca. 1960-1995
Special Collections M0785
Varela, Willie.
6.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1995.
Biography
A prolific and noted Super-8 filmmaker, programmer, and advocate. In the 1970s and early 1980s, Varela's extensive public programming as founder and director of SWAMP-El Paso (Southwestern Alternative Media Project) became the subject of a bitter censorship struggle, receiving national attention. Since the mid-1980s, his work has become increasingly political and since 1992 he has turned to Hi-8 video as well as narrative. Throughout his career, Varela's work has explored social space and cultural identity from the perspective of a deeply historical understanding of both experimental film/video and Chicano culture in South Texas.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts and publications of essays in support of Super-8 film and of the media arts, scripts, notebooks, clipping files, exhibition flyers and books, journal publications, audiotapes of interviews (four of Varela, three by Varela of Paul Sharits, Stan Brakhage, and Andrej Zdravic), and videotapes.
Access Terms
Anger, Kenneth.; Baillie, Bruce.; Barrie, Dianne.; Brabner, Wendy.; Brakhage, Stan.; Broughton, James.; Cannon, Terry.; Clancy, Patrick.; Dick, Vivienne.; Doberman, Gary.; Doby, Alex.; Espana, Frances Salome.; Friedman, Adele.; Friedrich, Su.; Gamboa, Harry, Jr.; Gardner, Chris.; Gerstein, David.; Gekiere, Madeline.; Gottheim, Larry.; Gidal, Peter.; Greenfield, Amy.; Guttenplan, Howard.; Haslanger, Martha.; Herrera, Raul Lopez.; Hudina, Chuck.; Huot, Robert.; Jost, Jon.; Keller, Marjorie.; Kilchesty, Albert.; Kren, Kurt.; Kuchar, George.; Lattanzi, Barbara.; Lee, David.; Lerman, Richard.; Lerner, Jesse.; Lipzin, Janis.; Lyon, Danny.; MacDonald, Scott.; Mekas, Jonas.; Murphy, J.J.; Nava, Greg.; Poe, Amos.; Posner, Bruce.; Rubin, Peter.; Sabal, Robert.; Scaff, Bill.; Schneemann, Carolee.; Schneider, Rosalind.; Sharits, Paul.; Sondheim, Alan.; Strand, Chick.; Vasquez, Gustavo.; Vasulka, Woody.; Vigil, Carmen.; White, John.; Zdravic, Andrej.; Canyon Cinema Cooperative.; Creative Arts Public Service Program.; Encounter Cinema.; Santa Barbara Independent Film Museum.; Mexican American art.; Mexican Americans.; Audio tapes.; Motion picture plays.; Video recordings.
Container List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE--PEOPLE FILES
  - Anger, Kenneth. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2 SWAMP letters 9/7/80 & 9/17/80
    - 2 letters 9/22/80 & 11/15/80
  - B., Beth and Scott. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "BB Movies" (film reviews/screenings) 1978-1981
    - "Present B Movies" (film reviews) 1979-1980
    - 1 letter n.d.
  - Baillie, Bruce. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 3 postcards 10/2/84, 11/17/84, & 9/27/85
  - Barrie, Dianne. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Filmography 1969-1979
    - Reviews of films 1974-1979
    - 1 b.w. photograph signed "Fondest Regards - Mizz 'B'"
    - (Frame blowup from "My Version of the Fall" 1978)
    - 7 letters 4/26/79 - 5/20/83
    - 4 postcards n.d., 8/29/79, 9/17/79, 2/12/80
    - 3 flyers "Exquisite Peril is Our Eternal Truth" n.d.
  - Brabner, Wendy. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 3 letters 1/17/82, 10/3/82, & 12/2/82
    - 1 biography n.d.
    - Brakhage, Stan. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 25 letters 1/28/80 - 4/16/90
    - 9 postcards 5/2/81 - 11/1/92
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Stan Brakhage 5/23/88
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Anton Brakhage 4/16/90
    - 2 color photographs of unidentified children n.d.
  - Brakhage, Stan (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 10 letters 3/10/76 - 11/20/79
    - Articles on Stan Brakhage 11/24/77 - 4/23/78
    - Film reviews 1978-1980
    - 2 postcards 3/15/79 & 11/16/79
    - "Film Culture" subscription flyer n.d.
    - 1 biography n.d.
  - Brakhage, Stan (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 7 letters 1/67 - 5/30/85
    - 1 article on Stan Brakhage n.d.
    - 2 napkins with hieroglyphics and writing n.d.
  - Brakhage, Stan (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 3 b.w. photographs of Stan & Jane Brakhage at SWAMP 10/11/79
    - 1 photo-reproduction of infant's head n.d.
    - 3 "Brakhage Films" catalogs n.d.
    - 4 color photographs of Brakage filmstrips n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph "Still from Blue Moses" n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph "Sexual Meditation: Office Suite" n.d.
    - 2 b.w. photographs of Stan Brakhage n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of unidentified man walking up stairwell n.d.
  - Broughton, James. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Film reviews 1973-1981
    - 5 letters 7/18/80 - 11/24/81
    - 4 postcards 8/25/80 - 5/20/81
    - 1 flyer "An Informal Evening with James Broughton" n.d.
    - 3 b.w. photographs "The Gardener of Eden" n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Joel Singer n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of James Broughton n.d.
  - Cannon, Terry. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Review of recent Jerry Tartaglia films 1977-1980
    - 17 letters 2/15/80 - 10/21/85
    - 5 Pasadena Filmforum brochures 5/17/81 - 12/18/81
    - 1 postcard 10/24/82
    - 1 Mexican Arts Symposium (M.A.S.) brochure 1983
    - 1 Filmforum brochure 1984
  - Cannon, Terry (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1 flyer "L.A. Filmworks" 1981
    - 8 Pasadena Filmforum posters 1981
    - 2 Pasadena Filmforum posters 1982
    - 7 Pasadena Filmforum Program Notes 1/18/82 - 2/17/82
  - Canyon Cinema Cooperative/Michael Wallins. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 9 letters 1/4/79 - 4/1/1981
    - 1 postcard 5/23/80
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum Program Notes flyer 12/1/80
    - 1 flyer "End of the Art World" n.d.
    - 2 flyers "A Celebration of Canyon Cinema" n.d.
  - Creative Arts Public Service Program (CAPS). (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1 list of CAPS tape titles (Program I-III) 1976-1979
    - 1 1979-1980 CAPS "Traveling Video Festival" schedule
    - 4 letters 7/30/80 - 9/8/80
  - Clancy, Patrick. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1 Paseo Video flyer 5/74
    - 5 letters 9/30/80 - 10/14/82
    - 2 postcards 3/81 & 6/17/81
    - 1 "Marginal Works: Atopia - No Man's Land" exhibition flyer 3/27/80 - 4/11/80
    - 1 Paseo Video review n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Pat Clancy n.d.
  - Dick, Vivienne. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1 Filmhouse music and film reviews 1955-1980
    - 1 Village Voice article 1979
    - 1 "Beauty Becomes the Beast" flyer n.d.
    - 1 "The Other Cinema" film review n.d.
    - 1 letter n.d.
  - Doberman, Gary. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1 letter with "New York Cut the Crap" paper by Gary Doberman 2/26/78
    - 7 letters 7/7/79 - 5/1/84
    - 1 poster "The ASUNM Film Committee Presents the Union (Sub) Theatre Films for Spring 1978"
  - Doby, Alex. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 14 letters 8/23/76 - 12/8/82
    - 5 postcards 7/28/77 - 1978
  - Encounter Cinema. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 2 letters 2/23/77 & 10/29/79
    - 1 Vanguard Newsletter 2/77
    - 3 Encounter Cinema flyer schedules 1979-1981
    - 1 Theatre Vanguard generic information letter n.d.
  - Espana, Frances Salome. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 5 letters 5/8/92 - 4/12/92
  - Friedman, Adele. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1 letter with resume, film titles, and review 4/8/82
  - Friedrich, Su. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1 "Gently Down the Stream" poem n.d.
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 1 "Comments on Scar Tissue" n.d.
    - 1 "Gently Down the Stream" film description n.d.
    - 1 resume n.d.
    - 1 "Graph of Scar Tissue" n.d.
    - 1 "Class Assignment" n.d.
  - Gamboa, Harry Jr. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 2 letters 12/1/92 & 8/17/93
  - Gardner, Chris. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 2 letters 8/5/80 & 4/2/81
    - 1 Fall 1980 "Rice Film Schedule"
  - Gianikian, Yervant, and Lucchi, Angela Ricci. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum Program Notes 6/30/80
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum "Dear Film Programmer" letter 12/1/80
    - 2 letters 5/8/81 & 5/24/81
    - 1 Millenium Film Workshop flyer 10/17/81
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum Program Notes 11/9/81
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum October- December film schedule n.d.
    - 1 "The Scented Films" catalogue and review n.d.
    - 1 "Angela Ricchi - Yervant Gianikian" Galleria Corsini - Intra catalogue n.d.
  - Gidal, Peter. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1 Bio/filmography n.d.
    - 1 National Film Theatre Programme Note n.d.
    - 1 "Notes for Program of Films" by Peter Gidal n.d.
  - Gerstein, David. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 4 letters 5/27/81 - 7/23/81
    - 1 postcard 6/2/81
    - 1 film biography n.d.
    - 2 b.w. photographs (unidentified individual) n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph (bridge of an unidentified ship) n.d.
  - Gekiere, Madeline. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 3 letters n.d.
    - 1 film biography n.d.
  - Gottheim, Larry. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1 article from "Film Culture" 1979
    - 2 postcards 7/23/81 & 9/21/81
    - 1 letter 11/9/81
    - 1 film commentary/poem n.d.
    - 1 Whitney Museum of American Art "Elective Affinities" Film Series Schedule
  - Greenfield, Amy. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1 letter with resume and fim/tape biography 11/23/80
  - Guttenplan, Howard (Millennium). (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1 article "Exhibiting Independent Film: The Millenium" 5/73
    - 1 article "Studio International" 6/74
    - 2 Millenium Personal Cinema flyers 1975 & 1976 (with March 1976 workshop calendar & film equipment loan form '75-'76
    - 1 Museum of Modern Art Department of Film Cineprobe Announcement 6/17/75
    - 2 letters 3/30/76 & 12/22/76
    - 1 article "Movie Journal" 12/16/76
    - 8 Millenium Personal Program flyers 1/29/78 - 12/81
    - 2 Anthology Fim Archives flyers 5/81
    - 2 film biographies n.d.
  - Haslanger, Martha. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1 letter with film lists 12/5/79
    - 1 letter 3/7/80
    - 1 letter with "Filmmakers Writing About Film" flyer 8/25/80
  - Herrera, Raul Lopez. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 5 letters 9/2/81 - 4/31/83
  - Hudina, Chuck. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1 letter with "Howie" film flyer 11/27/80
  - Huot, Robert. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1 article "An Interview With Robert Huot" 2/80
    - 1 article "Surprise! The Films of Robert Huot: 1967 to 1972" 1980
    - 1 newsletter "The Evening News" 1981
    - 1 letter with resume 3/18/81
    - 1 Marion Faller Photograph Exhibit announcement 3/22/81-4/17/81
    - 1 letter with hand-written film program 6/5/81
    - 1 letter with Millenium Personal Cinema Program flyer (5/8/82)
    - 2 photocopies of "Huot Show", Utica College (3-4/82) 5/26/82
    - 4 postcards 8/24/82 - 8/83
    - 1 Robert Huot Diaries catalogue n.d.
    - 1 Carol Kline Paintings catalogue n.d.
  - Jost, Jon. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1 letter 11/10/81
  - Keller, Marjorie. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 2 letters 1/22/83 & 3/3/83
    - 3 postcards 5/2/83 - 72183
  - Kilchesty, Albert. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 10 letters 11/18/80 - 12/16/93
    - 1 "In Progress" film description n.d.
  - Kren, Kurt. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1 flyer "Kurt Kren U.S.A. Tour, 1980"
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 1 flyer "Retrojspective of 20 years of film.. ." n.d.
    - 1 Biographical Information n.d.
    - 1 Touring Filmmakers flyer n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Kurt Kren n.d.
  - Kuchar, George. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 3 letters 8/14/90 - 9/9/91
    - 1 letter n.d.
  - Lattanzi, Barbara. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 2 film notes 1980 & 1981
    - 1 letter 3/1/82
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 1 resume n.d.
  - Lee, David. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 3 letters 2/23/81 - 11/6/81
    - 1 "Cinema Maudit" David Lee Film flyer 2/12/81
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 1 postcard n.d.
    - 12 "obscenity" film flyers n.d.
    - 1 article "Filmmaker to screen work" n.d.
  - Lerman, Richard. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1 letter 10/9/84
    - 2 letters 10/20/84
    - 1 postcard 3/10/84
    - 12 pages film/choreography program notes and reviews 1971-1981
    - 1 "Sound Images Events" flyer n.d.
  - Lerner, Jesse. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 3 letters 7/9/93 - 5/23/94
    - 2 essays "A Fragmented Subject Adrift" n.d.
  - Lipzin, Janis. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 15 film program notes and reviews 1975 - 1982
    - 1 b.w. photograph of "Periodic Vibrations.. " frames 1976
  - Lipzin, Janis (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Janis Lipzin as Amelia Earhart 1978
    - 1 b.w. photograph of "Visible Invetnory Nine" 1981
    - 1 "Recent Films" postcard, 1981
    - 1 "Recent Work in Film and Photography" flyer 1982
    - 1 resume n.d.
  - Lyon, Danny. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1 letter 5/2/80
  - MacDonald, Scott. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 3 letters 5/7/81 - 6/2/81
    - 1 El Paso Herald Post newspaper 7/31/81
    - 5 letters n.d.
    - 1 postcard n.d.
    - 1 "Minimal Films" list n.d.
    - 1 SWAMP Scott MacDonald "Minimal Film" flyer n.d.
  - Mekas, Jonas. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 2 letters 5/27/81 & 1/10/91
  - Murphy, J.J. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 3 letters 1/14/80 - 3/18/80
  - Nava, Greg. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 2 letters 8/20/84 & 10/3/84
  - Poe, Amos. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 3 postcards 5/7/79 - 2/20/80
    - 1 letter 6/11/79
    - 1 "Punk Pictures" flyer n.d.
  - Politicians. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1 letter 3/30/81
      (U.S. Congressman Fred Richmond)
    - 1 letter 5/20/81
      (U.S. Congressman Richard C. White)
    - 1 letter 5/25/81
      (Texas State Senator H. Tati Santiesteban)
    - 1 letter 5/28/81
      (U.S. Senator Lloyd Benston)
  - Posner, Bruce. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 2 letters 12/12/88 & 4/22/91
  - Rubin, Peter. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1 article "RVC film showings set today" 5/26/81
    - 1 Northwest Film Study Center Program Notes flyer 6/4/81
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 1 Holland Experimental Film "Filmmakers" list n.d.
    - 1 "The Vegetarians" film flyer n.d.
    - 1 SWAMP "Holland Experimental Film" flyer n.d.
  - Sabal, Robert. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 2 b.w. photographs of Robert Sabal 8/81
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 5 notecards n.d.
    - 1 "Films by Robert Sabal" notecard n.d.
    - 2 "Films by Robert Sabal" flyers n.d.
    - 2 "Robert Sabal Filmmaker" flyers n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Robert Sabal n.d.
  - Santa Barbara Independent Film Museum/Durst, Dee. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 5 letters 9/22/77 - 4/12/78
    - 1 postcard n.d.
    - 1 "Underground Cinema Expo" poster n.d.
  - Scaff, Bill. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 5 photocopies of "Coolage by William Scaff" 12/10/80
    - 1 letter 12/27/80
    - 1 letter in pen and crayon with nude photographs from "Sunshine & Health" (3/62) and "Official Journal of the American Sunbathing Association, Inc." (2/57) periodicals n.d.
    - 1 Filmography n.d.
    - 1 b.w photograph of William Scaff
  - Schneemann, Carolee. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1 "Works by Carolee Schneemann" 1976 Pocket Planner
    - 1 photocopy from "Up To & Including Her Limits" 6/76
    - 4 letters 12/6/76 - 5/1/77
    - 1 postcard 12/26/78
    - 1 stricle "Object vs. Persona" 5/83
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 2 postcards n.d.
  - Schneider, Rosalind. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 3 photocopies of interview article "Film As Art As Film" 11/21/74
    - 1 letter with filmography 7/10/80
    - 2 letters 8/1/80 & 10/25/80
    - 2 "The Clip" Newsletters Nov.-Dec 1980 & Jan.-Feb 1981
    - 2 photocopies of article "Artist Shifts Focus to a Film Project" 1/4/81
    - 1 Pasadena Filmforum Program Notes 11/3/80
    - 1 "Encounter Cinema" program announcement 11/6/80
  - Sharits, Paul. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - 1 letter with (5) film program notes 9/15/80
    - 1 postcard 10/6/80
    - 1 letter n.d.
    - 5 SWAMP presents Shartis announcements n.d.
  - Sondheim, Alan. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 2 letters n.d.
  - Strand, Chick & Marty. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 15 letters 11/30/82 - 2/4/90
    - 1 article "Light and Lost Bells" 1981
    - 1 article "Filmmaker to discuss her works" 1/22/82
    - 2 letters n.d.
  - Vasquez, Gustavo. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 2 letters 12/9/82 & 4/2/83
    - 1 postcard 5/22/83
  - Vasulka, Woody & Steina (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 3 photocopies of southwestern alternate media project notes 10/18/80
    - 2 b.w. photograph film stills n.d.
    - 2 b.w. photographs of Woody Vasulka
    - 2 b.w. photographs of Steina Vasulka
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Woody & Steina Vasulka
  - Vigil, Carmen. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 8 postcards 12/15/78 - 6/18/84
    - 6 letters 6/10/77 - 3/13/80
    - 1 handwritten note n.d.
    - 1 b.w. photograph of Carmen Vigil n.d.
  - White, John. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 2 letters 2/3/83 & 9/7/84
    - 1 photocopy of photos with unidentified parents and infant n.d.
  - Zdravic, Andrej. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1 handwritten document "A Talk With Andrej Zdravic by Willie Varela" 5/25&26/80
    - 1 letter 5/8/80
    - 1 letter with article "In West Texas.. ." (5/4/84) 10/31/84
    - 2 postcards 4/10/80 & 4/29/81
    - 1 letter with filmography and reviews n.d.
    - 4 Andrej Zdravic Sound Activated Films flyers n.d.
    - 1 Anthony Gap Saloon & Dance Hall April Calendar n.d.
    - 1 press release n.d.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (In). (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1 letter from Robert Haller 4/2/80
    - 1 letter from Steven Aronson 6/4/80
    - 1 letter from Anna Gronau 11/4/80
    - 1 letter from Diane Koszarski 1/30/81
    - 1 letter form Jim Hoberman 2/4/81
    - 1 letter from Arlene Zeichner 3/10/81
    - 1 letter from Jane Gutteridge & Anna Gronau 4/11/81
    - 1 letter with photocopies of film reviews from Arlene Zeichner 4/27/81
    - 1 letter from L.Wade Black 8/25/81
    - 1 letter from Joseph R. Murphy 11/11/81
    - 2 letters from Gordon 11/27/81 & 12/8/81
    - 1 color picture postcard from the Yasunori family 12/20/81
    - 1 letter from Richard 3/15/82
    - 1 letter from Michaelle McLean 7/21/82
    - 1 letter from Bruce Conner 11/10/82
    - 1 letter from Joe Gibbons 2/2/83
    - 1 letter from Sharon Taylor 2/10/83
    - 1 letter from Barbara Smith 3/22/83
    - 1 letter from Bruce Breland 6/30/83
    - 1 letter from Gary Kardish 7/7/83
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (In) (Contd.). (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1 postcard from Richard 8/20/83
    - 1 postcard from Bev E. 8/23/83
    - 1 postcard from DB 9/8/83
    - 1 letter with resume and article "A Political Farce" (1/29/83) from Alfredo Nunez 10/4/83
    - 1 postcard from Warren Sanbert 10/29/83
    - 1 postcard from lervant & Angela 1984
    - 1 postcard from Lucy Lippard 2/29/84
    - 1 postcard from Anne 6/3/84
    - 1 postcard from Steve 7/4/84
    - 1 postcard from Yoshiko Nojima 8/6/84
    - 1 (cc:) letter from Victoria Wozniak 10/9/84
    - 1 letter "Collective for Living Cinema" with notecard & "The Films of Willie Varela" program notes 3/25/85
    - 1 letter from Bob (Brodsky & Treadway) 4/7/85
    - 1 handwritten letter from Peter Heintz 10/28/85
    - 1 letter from Jerry 2/3/92
    - 1 letter from Rosa Linda Fregoso 5/31/92
    - 1 letter from Char 8/28/92
    - 1 letter from Armando Cristeto 1/31/94
    - 1 letter from John Reiger n.d.
    - 1 letter from Michael n.d.
    - 1 "Santa Illustrated" Christmas card from Michael n.d.
    - 1 letter from Michael Guccioni n.d.
    - 1 letter from Robert Rayher n.d.
    - 1 handwritten letter from Jane Collings n.d.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Out). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1 letter to Scott 1/17/84
    - 1 letter to Dear Friends at Starving Artists Times 1/26/84
    - 1 letter & photocopy dupicate of letter to Lucy Lippard 1/30/84
- SERIES II: PERSONAL FILES
  - Curriculum Vita n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Filmography n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- SERIES III: SUBJECT FILES
  - Censorship. Business Correspondence 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Censorship. Letters of Support 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Censorship. Film Notes 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Censorship. Press Clippings (El Paso) 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lost Man. Journal n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lost Man. Production Notes on Index Cards n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lost Man. Related Material 1991 - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lost Man. Script/Treatment 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Border Stories. Scripts n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - In Progress. Film Description n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Politically Correct. Dialogues n.d. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Voice-Overs. Text n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Proposals. Various 1988-1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Memories of the Dead. Contract 5/20/85 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Photos n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - El Ojo Apasionado. Program Notes 1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Press Releases 1981 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - SWAMP. Evaluation Report Form 1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - SWAMP. Exhibition Programs 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - SWAMP. Miscellaneous 1979-1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - SWAMP. Press Clippings 1976-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - SWAMP. Press Releases n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Super-8. Catalogue 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fiat Lux 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wall Caption. El Paso Museum n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Programs 1975-1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Programs 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Programs 1981-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Spiral 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Manuscripts. Unpublished 1975-1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts. Unpublished 1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Varela Publications 1976-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Stan Brakhage. Rare Interview 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Varela Citations in Print 1980-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Artweek. Reviews 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Film Reviews 1974-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- SERIES IV: MISCELLANEOUS PUBLICATIONS FILES
  - 1993 Biennial Exhibition (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Independent America: New Film 1978-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cinemanews No. 1980-6/1981-1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Cinemanews No. 81, 2-6 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Correspondence: The International Super 8 Phenomenon (2 copies) 1986 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Light Struck Winter 1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Light Struck Jan./Feb./Mar. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Perfect World in Contemporary Texas Art 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Jump Cut: A Review of Contemporary Media #39, June 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Afterimage: A Publication of the Visual Studies Workshop, December 1992 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 1995 Biennial Exhibition (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Blimp: Film Magazine 27/28, Spring 1994 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Rio Grande Review 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Film Quarterly, Spring 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Spiral No. 1/ October 1984, (2 copies) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Spiral No. 2/ January 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Spiral No. 6/ January 1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Videoforum: A Videography for Libraries (Latino Issue) Vol. 2, Summer 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Capirotada: Eight El Paso Artists 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Canyon Cinema Film/Video Catalog 7, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Cine Chicano n.d. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- SERIES V: MEDIA FILES - AUDIO & VIDEO CASSETTES
  - Stan Brakhage Interview 3/76 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Interview with jWillie Varela 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Andrej Zdravic Interview 5/25/80 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Paul Sharits Conversation 12/30/80 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Super 8 Film Soundtracks 1982-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Location Sound for Super 8 Films - Various 1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Willie Varela Interview 1983 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Location Sound for Various Super Shots 1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Spiral 3 April 1985 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Willie Varela at Filmforum June 23, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Photomercenary Production 1990 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - A Lost Man Inteviews KCOS-TV 9/92 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Film Soundtrack 6/91 & Interview on KTEP 1993(?) (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Original Synthesizer Music for A Lost Man Dec. 1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Film in the Video Era n.d. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - The Desert Within n.d. (Box 9, Folder 16)
- SERIES VI: OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Scrapbook 1978-1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1980-1986 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1 poster "Into the '80's: A Festival of New Film" n.d. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Accession 97-010
  - Four videos: 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Making is choosing